<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and exact relation of all the proceedings of Sir Hugh Cholmleys revolt, deserting the Parliament, and going to the Queen, with the regaining of Scarborough Castle, by the courage and industry of Capt. Bushel. Sent in two letters, the one from Sir Iohn Hotham to M. Speaker, the other, from a worthy Captain to a member of the honourable House of Commons. Die Martis 4 Aprilis 1643. It is ordered by the Commons in Parliament, that these two letters concerning Sir Hugh Cholmley's Revolt, and the re-taking of Scarborough Castle, shall be forthwith printed and published. H. Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
            <author>Hotham, John, Sir, d. 1645 Jan. 2.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2909A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E95_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21968</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871556</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871556</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155802</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86597)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155802)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 17:E95[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and exact relation of all the proceedings of Sir Hugh Cholmleys revolt, deserting the Parliament, and going to the Queen, with the regaining of Scarborough Castle, by the courage and industry of Capt. Bushel. Sent in two letters, the one from Sir Iohn Hotham to M. Speaker, the other, from a worthy Captain to a member of the honourable House of Commons. Die Martis 4 Aprilis 1643. It is ordered by the Commons in Parliament, that these two letters concerning Sir Hugh Cholmley's Revolt, and the re-taking of Scarborough Castle, shall be forthwith printed and published. H. Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
                  <author>Hotham, John, Sir, d. 1645 Jan. 2.</author>
                  <author>Worthy captain.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Best, and are to be sold at his Shop neer Gray's Inne-gate in Holborn,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643. April 7.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In this edition line 7 reads: of Scarborough Castle,.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bushell, Brown, d. 1651.</term>
               <term>Cholmley, Hugh, --  Sir, 1600-1657.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Campaigns --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scarborough (England) --  History, Military --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155802:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A true and exact RELATION Of all the proceedings of Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmleys</hi> Revolt, deſerting the Parliament, and going to the Queen, with the regaining of <hi>Scarborough</hi> Caſtle, by the courage and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of Capt. <hi>Buſhel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sent in two Letters, the one from Sir</hi> Iohn Hotham <hi>to M.</hi> Speaker, <hi>the other, from a worthy Captain to a Member of the honourable Houſe of Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Die Martis</hi> 4 <hi>Aprilis</hi> 1643.</bibl>
               <p>It is this day ordered by the Commons in Parliament, that theſe two Letters concerning Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley's</hi> Revolt, and the re-taking of <hi>Scarborough</hi> Caſtle, ſhall be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>H. Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Richard Best,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop neer <hi>Gray's</hi> Inne-gate in Holborn, 1643.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 7.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:155802:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155802:2"/>
            <head>A Letter from Sir <hi>IOHN HOTHAM</hi> to Maſter Speaker of the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am very ſorry, I have this unhappy occaſion to write to you, which is Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmleys</hi> Revolt; who has of late taken a Commiſſion from the King, for the forces hee had raiſed by authority of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; for the Caſtle of <hi>Scarborough;</hi> It ſeems he thought at firſt to have carried it ſo cloſely, as to have (before I perceived) retired all hee had in this Towne, and for that purpoſe ſent Captaine <hi>Buſhell</hi> with a Ship and ſeven peeces of Ordnance in her; But as God would have it, I had the night before a ſecret intelligence ſent me of it, and ſo have the Ship and Ordnance ſure: And thereupon inſtantly diſpatched a Catch to Captaine <hi>Haddock,</hi> and our Ships that ride Northward to give them notice of it, leſt little ſuſpecting his revolt they might put into that Haven and be entrapped, and my Catch being at Sea well mann'd and having in her four ſmall Guns, met with a <hi>Scarborough</hi> Ship and Ammunition going from the Parliament to him, which was three pieces of Ordinance, twenty barrels of powder, forty Carabines, ſome Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols and Swords, and two great Fats of Match, all which they ſeiſed upon, and brought hither, and it ſhall, God willing, be better employed. Captain <hi>Buſhell</hi> proteſts deeply his innocency, and more then that he was to bring back ſome of Sir <hi>Hughs</hi> things from <hi>Hull,</hi> he knew not any thing of the buſineſſe, and ſweares to mee hee will doe his utmoſt ſervice for you. Moſt of Sir <hi>Hughs</hi> Officers, and a very great many both of his horſe and foot have forſaken him, and are now at <hi>Hull</hi> with mee: Sir <hi>Thomas Nortcliff,</hi> a ſon in law of mine came from him to mee yeſternight with thirty good horſe, and tels me he hopes, the reſt will follow his Captaine, Lievtenant <hi>Vanderhurſt</hi> came with him. Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Ledgard</hi> a Kinſman of mine, that I ſent from hence, hath likewiſe left him: But Lievtenant Colonell <hi>Alured</hi> was the firſt that conſented to joyn with him in this bad action. Thus have I truly related to you by my firſt opportunity, the whole progreſſe of this unfortunate attempt wherein hee hath utterly loſt himſelf, but God be bleſt, done your buſineſſe no prejudice.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:155802:3"/>
            <p>The two Dutchmen are exceeding gallant men, and have done you very good ſervice, the ones name is <hi>Froome,</hi> the other <hi>Vanderhurſt;</hi> I have in your name, aſſured them of your conſtant reſpect to all fidelity. Sir, there ſhall no oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of doing the Houſe ſervice ſcape mee; and ſince I ſent Captaine <hi>Buſhell</hi> thither, hee has performed his Truſt gallantly, impriſoned one <hi>Iames Cholmley,</hi> whom Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> had left there; and ſeized upon the Caſtle. I ſent my Catch with more Souldiers to relieve him, and twenty pound to the Souldiers in the Caſtle to drink.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sir, I ever remayne your moſt humble Servant, Iohn Hotham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I cannot but believe you have already heard of the rendring the Caſtle of <hi>Scarborough,</hi> by Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley</hi> to the Cavaliers, yet becauſe (it may be) ſome may be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be ſatisfied how it comes to paſſe that a Fort of that ſtrength ſhould be put into another hand without bloud, to give you &amp; al the world ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that particular, I have addreſſed theſe unto you being my old friend and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and blame me not (I beſeech you) if in doing it I exceed the bounds of a Letter, for I deſire to ſet forth all the circumſtances according to truth, and when I have ſo done let the blame ſtick where it is, I hope my ſelfe and other the Officers who quitted the employment, ſhall appeare to be honeſt men, and to have done nothing but what was fit for thoſe who had a care of the publick, as well as their own private intereſts.</p>
            <p>Upon Friday the tenth of March (as I take it) Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley,</hi> to whoſe truſt the Caſtle was commited by Parliament, and by him to me in his abſence came to <hi>Scarborough</hi> from <hi>Beverley,</hi> whither upon the taking of <hi>Stamford</hi> bridge by the Enemy, he was retreated from <hi>Malton</hi> (it being conceived not tenable, as the Enemies forces then lay.) I dare not ſay that at his return thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he had any intention to betray the Caſtle, for the very next day, hee call'd my ſelfe and the reſt of his Officers to conſult touching the putting of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155802:3"/>forces into the Caſtle of <hi>Pickering,</hi> and the breaking downe <hi>Yeddingham,</hi> and <hi>How bridges</hi> for the preſervation of <hi>Pickeringlythe</hi> which all of us concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be very neceſſary, and for that purpoſe Captaine <hi>Froom,</hi> a German, who commanded his owne troope, Sir <hi>Tho: Nortcliffe</hi> with his troop of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gooners, and another troop of Dragooners commanded by one Lievtenant <hi>Strangways</hi> (<hi>Medley</hi> the Captaine being formerly taken priſoner at <hi>Yarum</hi>) were ſent abroad, but by the way they found the Enemy was got before them, and had poſſeſſed themſelves of <hi>Pickering</hi> Towne and Caſtle with ſome other Towns not far diſtant, and had placed divers Muſquetiers at <hi>How</hi> bridge (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt conſiderable) for the ſecuring of that paſſage againſt us: So that it was utterly impoſſible for them without certain ruine, or at leaſt extream dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to effect that they were ſent for. Yet falling happily upon ſome of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies forces at <hi>Thornton,</hi> who were newly come thither from plundring Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> and his Tenants at <hi>Fyling</hi> they reſolved to charge them, which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly they did, not ſurprizing them in their quarters, as was falſly ſuggeſted by the other party: for Captain <hi>Froom,</hi> cauſed a Piſtoll to be diſcharged at the Town end, and a Drum to be beat a quarter of a mile ere he came to the Towne, by which the Enemy had the alarme, and put themſelves in a poſture of defence, but God gave the victory to us, and delivered into our hands one and twenty priſoners, of which one was a Serjeant Major, another a Captain, a 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. a Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, two Cornets, with one of their Colours two Quarter-maſters, three Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals, a Trumpeter and a Farrier, the reſt were common Troopers, there being at that time two or three Troops more of the Enemy within 12 ſcore (who had not the ſpirit to aſſiſt their fellows) and neere upon 500 more within a mile or two, which occaſioned our men (having intelligence of it) not to proſecute that ſucceſſe ſo fully as otherwiſe they would if the Enemy had been further di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant: Theſe priſoners were brought to <hi>Scarborough,</hi> where they were uſed with all humanity (wherein it muſt be acknowledged, hee hath not been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wanting to any he hath heretofore taken; notwithſtanding the cruell uſage of his men which were taken at <hi>Yarum:</hi> After ſome time letters paſſed betwixt him, Collonel <hi>Goring</hi> and others, and upon one day two Trumpets came to <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough,</hi> the one from Collonell <hi>Goring</hi> at <hi>Yorke,</hi> the other from Sir <hi>Francis Mackworth</hi> at <hi>Thornton</hi> where the forementioned conflict was, and where the Enemy at that time lay quartered. My ſelfe and others were made believe theſe Trumpets came for exchange of Priſoners; though I confeſſe I wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red much two Trumpets ſhould come from two places at one time for one and the ſame buſineſſe; Yet ſuch was my reſpect unto him, and my confidence in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155802:4"/>his fidelity, that I ſoone anſwered my ſelfe, with this that it might well be, and ſo, ſaid nothing of it to any man. I doe not know what the contents of thoſe Letters were, but after that, I found, he would at ſeverall times advance the Kings and the Earle of <hi>Newcastles</hi> Forces, exceedingly undervaluing thoſe under the command of the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> hee often affirmed hee was ſleighted by the Parliament, to whom he had ſeverall times written for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, but could never obtain them in that meaſure that hee deſired. What his intentions were in it whither to ſound my fidelity, or for ſome other end I know not, but I indeavoured to give him as ſatisfactory an anſwer as I could, yet did not all this time imagine or conceit that he intended any way to defraud the truſt concreded to him by the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>James Cholmely</hi> his kinſman (whoſe ſonne ſerves the Earle of <hi>Craw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and who I feare hath had too great an influence upon him in this buſines) was afterward (as I imagine) ſent to <hi>Yorke</hi> about the effecting of this fine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, though at his returne he gave it out with many deep proteſtations that riding into the Country about ſome buſineſſe, hee was made priſoner by the Enemy about 6 miles from <hi>Scarborough,</hi> and carryed to <hi>Yorke,</hi> from whence by means of ſome friend and acquaintance he there meet with, hee ſaid, he had happily eſcaped.</p>
            <p>On Munday the 20. of March Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley</hi> rid early abroad with one ſervant onely, and leſt I ſhould ſuſpect ſomething, ſent one to me, to tell me he was gone to meet Sir <hi>John Hotham,</hi> that they might conſult touching the ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Forces to him for clearing that ſide of the Countreys: but he deſired if any asked for him, I ſhould ſay he was gone to <hi>Whitby</hi> his owne houſe to take care for the preſervation of it and the Towne, which had formerly made good expreſſions of fidelity to the King and Parliament. I expected he would have returned at night, but finding he did not, wondered at it, yet feared no change, becauſe I ſuſpected nothing, conceiving the place of meeting with Sir <hi>John Hotham,</hi> and the length of the conſultation might very well retard his returne till the next day. He then returned and told me, hee had ſtayd the night before at <hi>Ganton</hi> (a friends houſe to us both being 6 miles from <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough</hi>) which becauſe I knew nothing to the contrary, nor dreamed of any falſity, I did eaſily beleeve. On Thurſday morning he ſent Captaine <hi>Browne Buſhell</hi> to <hi>Hull</hi> with a ſmall Ship, which he and I, and ſome others had newly ſet forth to reſtraine proviſions for going to <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> with directions to bring from thence certain money and other things which lay there for him, but I was neither made acquainted with his going by Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> nor ſuſpected
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155802:4"/>any ill intentions for delivery of the Caſtle untill Friday betwixt 7 and 8 of the clock at night that he ſent for me up into the Caſtle (where he lay) and after ſome diſcourſe fell to magnifie the Kings forces, and at laſt told me plainly he was at <hi>Yorke</hi> on Munday before with the Queen, that he reſolved to hold the Caſtle for the King, and by Commiſſion from him, and that hee intended the next day ſo to declare himſelfe, asking me my reſolution concerning it. I told him, he gave me very ſhort warning; Yet I hoped (although I conceived he had dealt very ill with me being his neere kinſman, and whom hee had inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the ſame ſervice with him) to capitulate touching the rendring of the Caſtle without making me acquainted before hand with it that I might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for my owne ſafety) he would give me leave to uſe my conſcience, which he ſaid he was willing to doe; I then deſired him I might have liberty to paſſe to <hi>Hull</hi> with my wife and children, and that I might have a note from him to that purpoſe, which he promiſed to doe; and further, that if I were taken by the way, he would procure my inlargement. I ſpake to him further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his breach of truſt, and told him what a diſhonour it would bee to himſelfe, and what a ſtaine to his poſterity thus to violate it, and would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have perſwaded him to have continued faithfull, offering to goe poſt my ſelfe to <hi>London</hi> for him and to labour to obtaine ſuch conditions for him from the Parliament, as he ſhould approve and like of; But he anſwered he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged and reſolved to performe what hee had promiſed, and ſo I left him, and preſently went into the Town to conſult with a friend what courſe to run, but he not being within, I returned to my owne houſe. About ten of the clocke at night I received letters from <hi>Hull,</hi> by which I had notice of his reſolution, together with a packet to himſelfe from Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham,</hi> which becauſe I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived there might be in it ſome good advice, and for that I was deſirous hee ſhould conſult with his pillow about it, I was very carefull to ſee delivered, and therefore ſent one of my ſervants up with it to the Caſtle. It ſeemes the Letters were of another effect then I ſuſpected, for Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> having notice of his reſolution to render the Caſtle, and conceiving Captaine <hi>Buſhell</hi> was by him imployed to <hi>Hull</hi> with no good intent, and not knowing whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he might comply with him or not in that bad action, had made ſtay of Captain <hi>Buſhell,</hi> and the Ship, and thereof gave him notice by thoſe letters. He wiſht my man to tell me I ſhould come to him to the Caſtle in the morning, which accordingly I did; He told mee what Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> had done to <hi>Buſhell</hi> and that he muſt ſtay mee in lieu of him till hee were delivered, yet promiſed to protect mee from violence, and that I ſhould not receive the leaſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155802:5"/>prejudice, and upon my faith given not to ſtirre without his licence, he was content I ſhould walke at liberty. I preſently diſpatcht a meſſenger to <hi>Hull</hi> to give Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> notice of theſe proceedings, and indeavoured my ſelfe in the mean time to get my goods on Shipboard, that I might take an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of getting my Family and them away (if it might bee) though I ſtayed behinde my ſelfe. After my departure he ſent for Sir <hi>Thomas Norcliffe,</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Froom,</hi> Captaine <hi>Vanderhurſt</hi> a Dutchman, who commanded his Foot company, and other his Officers to whom hee imparted his reſolution. Sir <hi>Thomas Norcliffe</hi> ſo much miſliked the buſineſſe, that he preſently departed to <hi>Hull, Froom</hi> told him he would be ready to ſerve him in an honeſt way, but never uſed to bee of the Traytours company, <hi>Vanderhurſt</hi> and ſome others tooke time to deliberate. About nine of the clocke <hi>Froom, Vanderhurſt</hi> with about 8 or 9. troopers came to my houſe to adviſe with me what was to bee done; We debated the buſineſſe, and truly the Souldiers were very ill pleaſed that he dealt ſo with us, and ſhowed themſelves very forward to have mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched up to the Caſtle, and have made him priſoner. The men were all ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to me, and two of them to this Kingdome, and therefore I held it no great diſcretion to diſcover my ſelfe too far unto them whoſe hearts I knew not, nor whither ſome of them might not be ſent by him to ſift and circumvent me, and it may be, if I had ſhewed my ſelf extreme forward in it, ſome of them might have been jealous of me, becauſe I was his kinſman: I returned this anſwer; That for my owne part I would adventure my skin in the quarrell as freely as any man, but as for attempting to ſurprize the Caſtle, I could not aſſent unto it for theſe reaſons; It was a place of great ſtrength, and advantage to him that was then within it, The Inhabytants of the Towne were extreme malignant, wee had not felt the pulſe of the Souldiers, nor knew how they ſtood affected, nor what the Gunners intended to do, who were the men muſt do much of the buſineſſe if it came to action (three of which were but newly brought in by him, and one or two of thoſe three had formerly borne part in a mutiny which was made againſt one in the Towne by ſome ill affected perſons for which I had puniſht them, and therefore had the leſſe reaſon to truſt them.) But beſides all this, I told them there was a powerfull enemy at hand (or at leaſt within call) from whom we muſt expect certaine ruine if wee ſhould ſhow our ſelves, and not goe through with the buſineſſe as wee deſired. As we were thus debating the buſineſſe, comes one in and informes us, that there were two Troopes of horſe at the Townes end, which quite ſpoyled all our bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, for although the report was grounded upon a miſtake, either of ſome
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155802:5"/>Market people who were then comming to the Market, or elſe of Sir <hi>Thomas Norcliffes</hi> Dragoones, many of which went that day from <hi>Scarborough</hi> after their Captaine, yet becauſe it was not without probability, it cauſed us to breake off our diſcourſe, and this was the very reaſon why wee did nothing, for it could not ſinke into our heads that any man of diſcretion ſhould bee ſo impudent as to betray a Fort, and have no power of the Enemy to joyne with him in caſe he ſhould find oppoſition within, eſpecially when the chiefe Officers had not bin formerly conſulted with, nor their affections tryed, nor any party made amongſt the Souldiers, to make that good which was intended. After this I had ſeverall thoughts what to do. It grieved mee to ſee the Caſtle thus loſt, but I was jealous of my power to helpe it: Many things came into my mind, and a great conflict I had in my ſelfe touching the point of aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and whither in point of conſcience, it were lawfull without any by-ends of ones own to kill an Enemy to God and his Countrey, as my heart told me he was, and ſo taking him away in this ſin, ſend him in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to Hell. At laſt I reſolved <hi>in dubits, optimum eſt ſequi tutiorem partem,</hi> and therefore chuſed rather to watch an opportunity, if I could to make him priſoner, To which purpoſe I went up to the Caſtle, I conferred with ſeverall Souldiers, whom I found cordiall to the Cauſe, yet fearfull to ingage themſelves without good force to back them. I ſpoke with an Officer who muſt be name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, who ſeemed much to lament the Colonels Apoſtacy, and deſired of me to know what was to be done; I asked him if he would be honeſt, he proteſted he would, I wiſhed him then to clap to my Lievtenant (whom he had corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and who then ſtood like <hi>Cerberus</hi> keeping hell gates) as I would to the Colonell, and wee would make them both priſoners. Hee askt mee touching the affections of the Souldiers, I told him I was confident, they were right and would ſtick to us; ſo downe we went to the Guard together, to ſee the number of them, and to prepare them before hand for our intended deſigne: Juſt as wee were going downe came the Colonell, and three or foure of his ſervants armed with Piſtols, ſo that wee were forced to breake off our communication, and went along with him: As we came by the Guard he ſtayed and told the ſouldiers what he intended, but proteſted hee aymed at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but the peace of the Country and obedience to the King, I hearing that anſwered I hoped we had not bin in a way of rebellion all this time. At which word hee catched mee by the hand and calling for halfe a ſcore musket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires ſaid he would teach me to rule my tongue: I told him if he hangd me I muſt and would ſpeake having ſo good reaſon for it, and ſo was I carryed guarded with his ſervants and thoſe Muskettiers to his houſe where I remained
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155802:6"/>till upon ſetling of both our hot bloud, he was content to let me goe, with my wife, children, and goods to <hi>Hull,</hi> upon my promiſe firſt made to procure Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> to inlarge Captaine <hi>Buſhell</hi> within two dayes, or elſe returne to <hi>Scarborough</hi> within that time, which I aſſured him I would do; and therupon had his licence to depart that night by ſea for <hi>Hull.</hi> On Munday I there arrived and that day obtained <hi>Buſhels</hi> inlargement who the next day returned to <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough,</hi> but never got any thankes for it from him who ſeemed ſo tender over him as you ſhall heare afterwards. Captaine <hi>Froom,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Vanderhurſt</hi> followed me with almoſt all the troope, and divers of the foot ſouldiers who now ſerve under me at <hi>Hull,</hi> where by Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> I am againe put into imployment as are alſo the other two Captaines, <hi>Froom</hi> being made Captaine of the troup hee brought with him and <hi>Vanderhuſt</hi> his Lievtenant according to their owne deſires. And thus Sir, you have all the particular circumſtances of this bad action; let me begge your patience but a little and you ſhall have the ſecond part of the ſtory, which I hope will give both your ſelfe and all honeſt men better ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Buſhell</hi> (though Cozen German to the Collonell) did ſo little ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of his kinſmans ways that he made many proteſtations ere he went from <hi>Hull</hi> to recover the Caſtle thus perfidiouſly loſt. It fell out happily that Mr. <hi>Iames Cholmley</hi> a man of no great experience was made Captain of the Caſtle and <hi>Henry Buſhell</hi> (who is Captain <hi>Buſhells</hi> Brother) his lievtenant. The two brothers conferre together and at twelve of the Clock at night, on Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day laſt the Captain with 4 more was let in by his brother, who had prepared the Souldiers (ready enough to revolt from that ſide they liked not) with Beere and Tobacco, he acquainting the ſouldiers with his intentions, they promiſed to ſtick to him, the ſergeant who commanded the guard was layd hold on, the Gunners were next ſurprized; but ſwore fidelity, there was nothing left now but to get the Tower, a place of great ſtrength where the Captaine was lodged, and in which all the amunition and proviſions for the Caſtle were layd. For the effecting hereof the Serjeant was cauſed to knock at the gate and to tell the keeper of the Magazin who came to know what was the matter that there was an alarme in the Town and that the ſouldiers muſt be furniſht with powder and ſhott, Credit being given hereunto and the gate opened <hi>Buſhell</hi> entred with his ſouldiers, commanded the delivery of the keyes and thereby became Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Caſtle without one drop of bloud ſpilt on either ſide and in it of the new made Captain, and the next morning of one Captain <hi>Sunderland</hi> and ſome other Cavaliers who were come to rejoyce with their new gotten freind. And thus the Caſtle of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> which both in my owne and the opinion of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155802:6"/>many being well and ſufficiently provided is able to oppoſe an army of 10000 men was twice taken in one weeke: firſt by treachery, and afterwards by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt policy, and is now in the hands of Captain <hi>Buſhell,</hi> who vowes to hold it for the King and Parliament, and ſooner to blow up the fabrick then that ever it ſhould come into the hands of the Cavaliers: This day he writ Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> for aſſiſtance, which he hath taken care to be ſent to him to morrow morning. I hope the Parliament will thinke of him that recovered it, and give him ſuch requitall as ſhall incourage both him and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to adhere and ſtick cloſe unto them: I will trouble you no further at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent being weary with writing, If I may receive any letters from you the next week here at <hi>Hull,</hi> I ſhall be willing to hold Intelligence with you, and to let you know the paſſages of the North. However, Sir, I aſſure you none is more truly yours, then</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Hull Good-friday</hi> 
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your affectionate friend and ſervant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
